so this is the first suit of maim Manaya
Majik number one and it's called mul
which in English it's translated as the
root of All
Things So It Begins by describing um by
saying that the Buddha was staying near
ukat in the Suba forest and he was
talking to the
monks so he addressed
them saying um monks I will teach you
the explanation of the root of all
things listen and apply your minds well
I will
speak so the Buddha continues take an
unlearned ordinary person who has not
seen the noble ones and it's neither
skilled nor trained in the teaching of
the noble ones they have not seen true
persons and the neither skilled nor
trained in the teaching of true
persons so this is a description of a
putuj of somebody who does not have the
right view um so when the Buddha decided to
view um so when the Buddha decided to
begin this um exposition of the root of
all things like what is what is at the
root of anything that you might
experience um he started by with a with
a case of pjan so somebody uh who is not
suana who does not understand the way
out of
suffering um for that person the Buddha
says they perceive Earth is
Earth having perceived Earth is Earth
they conceive Earth they conceive in
Earth they conceive from Earth they
conceive Earth is mine they Delight in
Earth so first thing here it's as as you
will see obviously um the SU starts by
um listing earth water fire air the four
grade elements then goes into all sorts
of other
phenomena uh the point there is to to um
paint the picture of any direction
anything big small far or near personal
big small far or near personal
impersonal lofty coarse Sublime
Divine um the emphasis is that uh the root of
um the emphasis is that uh the root of
any of those things it's on the way puu
perceives it as it will become clearer
later on in the suta when the Buddha
speaks about the noble disciple and the
arand so the root of all things that
exist for pujan however lofty however
course is in his perception of them so
when he perceives those things he does
not understand that so when he perceives
he then conceives Earth he conceives
what he perceives he conceives in Earth
he conceives apart from Earth he
conceives Earth is mine he Delights in
Earth so these attitudes that are
described here um conceiving conceiving in
here um conceiving conceiving in
conceiving from conceiving mine
delighting in they're not like um linear
sort of uh linear um steps that puten is
doing um they're more like the uh
immediate implications of him already
Del Lighting in Earth so as the Buddha
said in in other suas be ignorance is
beginningless so you could uh obviously
infer here you could say the same that
um conceiving is beginningless there is
no like a time before which um augen did
not misconceive things and then he
started misconceiving them uh all all he
has or if he were to look in the
direction of earth water fire air gods
and so on he'll find him delighting in
phenomena first through that Delight he
can discern that there is conceiving so
whether he conceives Earth whether he
conceives in from apart he conceive it
as mine he conceives himself as separate
from that phenomenon so when he
perceives Earth is Earth through the
perception of Earth he puts himself
outside of that Earth so to speak in
other words he becomes the master the
owner the center the falr of the
experience that's pretty much the
definition of atada sense of self that's
independent of the five agregates um and
that's the point in the
suta somebody might wonder why does the
Buddha list all these not just all these
elements but then these gods and gods of
streaming radians and brahmas and stuff
it's just to show that on any plane of
existence on any layer in any direction
whatever can be
perceived pujan is misconceiving it not
because of the things he's perceiving
but because of his attitude of um of
delight and misconceiving of the
ownership of his perception he might not
conceive that he owns a Brahma but he's
if he were to perceive it for example
but he's certainly conceiving the
perception of sight the presence of
sight as his so that's why again the
point here it's not to look for the
specific things Mula the root of all
things means like the root of the
framework of all things so it's not
about specific things but it's about is
the most General representatives of the
framework of your senses of your mind of
your perception because that's where
these conceiving take
place um so having perceived Earth is
Earth TOA conceives Earth conceives in
Earth conceives from Earth conceive it
as mine he Delights in it why is that
because he has not completely understood
it
so the lack of understanding of his
perception of
Earth means there is going to be some
form of conceiving conceiving Earth in
apart means there will be sense of
ownership of perception sense of Mind
there will be Delight in things that are
then perceived uh on that secondary
level so the suta continues about water
so he perceives puan they perceive water
is water they perceive fire is fire um
they perceive air is air beings is
beings Gods is Gods the progenitor as
the progenitor Brahma is
Brahma those of string streaming
Radiance as those of streaming Radiance
replete with Glory as repl with Glory uh
abundant fruit those of abundant fruit
uh they perceive the Conqueror as the
Conqueror and so on so it carries on um
after covering all these all these
Realms all these possible things that
someone's even expanded mind might
perceive the point is the root of all of
that of the existence of all of that and
how it exists for you so to speak it
it's within in your own perception or
ignorance of it so as it says he Peres
all of that he conceives he conceives
his mind um he Delights in it because he
has not completely understood it then he
carries on to the dimension of Infinite
Space the dimension of infinite
Consciousness the dimension of
nothingness so these are the consider
those fin REM material mental
comprehensions and and establishments of
the Mind The Mention Of neither
perception or perception the the the
atut most one that a pjan could
technically uh establish his mind
correctly uh then it goes to the senses
anything that's seen
heard um sensed touched smelled thought
um sensed touched smelled thought
doesn't matter he will be misconceiving
it because he has not completely
understood the nature of perception or
in other words what he perceives he will
then automatically um I want to say
automatically um I want to say
automatically but really simultaneously
misconceive that's an again what I what
I said in the beginning there's no
starting point where there is a pure
perception of kjin a clean unadulterated
UNP perverted and then that somehow
gradually step by step gets infected
with these conceiving and then it
becomes mind becomes Delight that's a
linear explanation of somebody who is
approaching this from the the outside
point of view like the commentaries and
so on internally when you look at it
what you see is Delight within the
Delight you'll find ownership because it
will be impossible to Delight in things
unless you're already implying ownership
of perception that can find joy and
pleasure in these sense objects for
example within the ownership you're
going to find that that thing that
phenomena in its broadest presence
manifestation of
itself that thing is conceived as
something separate from you as something
over here or in here or apart from in
other words you
gratuitously um assume your own
standpoint of perceiving that thing as
too independent of that thing so to
speak you perceive it as an observer as
sorry you assume it as an observer as
something that is that is there
regardless of what's being perceived pan
certainly does not see that his sense of
self is undermined by he what he
perceives by random perceptions by any
perception it's undermined by the
presence of the
Aggregates so the S continues after it
lists all the senses then it goes to
anything that can be known anything that
can be
cognized um he hasn't fully understood
that's why he conceives then Oneness the
sense of Oneness the sense of diversity
and then goes to says the all the
broadest sense of his experience the
widest phenomenon of the all internal
external uh past future present doesn't
matter the perception of the all again
it was never the problem it was his not
understanding the nature of perception
of it that's how he conceives it so then
after the the perception all the says
they perceive nibana so PJ can actually
perceive the phenomenon of nibana like
as the sutas described nibana is a dhama
another phenomenon that has arisen that
is present and uh but it's the only
dharm that is aan dama which means the
dharm that's undetermined or deactivated
let's put it that way uh and by that
it's meant that within the experience
niban is to be found within the
experience of the five Aggregates so
it's not on the level
of a mystical phenomenon that will then
be be found outside of one's perception
outside of one's five Aggregates the
fact that it's listed here and there are
other sutas IM where the Buddha says yes
when somebody an outsider AJ he
describes and he says I'm attaining this
nibana this nibana is mine the would
have said fact what he's stating is what
nibana is but he's not um attaining it
he's not being established in it because
he still hasn't uprooted that
fundamental wrong view in regard to his
five he hasn't approved the so he's
taking the ownership of it so if you
wonder then what what is that nibana
well as I said it's nothing mystical
outside of the experience it cannot be I
mean saying that there is something
outside of experience on account of this
experience is another phenomenon that
you're designating within this
experience So nibana within this
experience is the phenomenon of complete
top to bottom dispassion in regard to
any phenomenon in the world so putuj
could technically if he's like very diligent
technically if he's like very diligent
restrained and obviously wise to a
degree could develop his mind to the
point that he experienced complete
dispassion in regard to everything past
present future far near big or small
Divine Sublime course but what he will
not be able to do is to experience
complete dispassion towards that
phenomenon of dispassion towards
anything obviously if a person does
develop that say
hypothetically and then they get to hear
the Buddha's teaching they'll probably
need like a half a sentence just for
that last thing to fall into place
because obviously the mind is already
developed but the point the Buddha
illustrates here that even
theana will be misconceived for somebody
who does not understand Earth is Earth
who is who is through perceiving it
misconceiving it and another reason what
another thing that's important to
mention here is that
um you have to um basically you have to
recognize that when it says he perceives
Earth as Earth for example his
perception is already affected with that
ignorance otherwise it would not be
simultaneously implying conceiving and
delight and the reason why I bring this
up is because it should certainly be
enough to do away with any contemporary
notion of practice that revolves around
perceiving and observing
impartially Sensations uh or just any general
Sensations uh or just any general
perceptions basically any methodical
approach to the practice that implies
neutrality of your observation it's
wrong because your perception is not
neutral if it were neutral it would not
lead to conceiving it would not lead it
would not imply conceiving it will not
imply ownership it will not imply
Delight but as the Buddha describes the
root of all for putuj is his Delight
which implies ownership which implies
conceiving which implies already
misperceiving so the bare awareness the
pure perception the the pristine seeing
of things it's not pristine for as long
as there is no right view so what P
puina thinks its objective perception
it's already his misappropriated sense
of ownership delighting in things that
he's perceiving
perceiving
um so then the Su continues and talks
about the trainee I the noble disciple
says among mon who is a trainee who
hasn't achieved their goal but he lives
aspiring to the Supreme Sanctuary from
the Yoke he directly knows Earth is
Earth so he doesn't say he perceives so
he's not perceiving it anymore because
perception is reserved for a Pena but's
perception is perception with aij with
ignorance um aana or higher has
understood the nature of that perception
so that's why when he perceives he
directly knows Earth is Earth having
directly known Earth is Earth let him
not conceive Earth let him not conceive
in Earth let him not conceive from Earth
let him not conceive Earth is mine
letting not the light in Earth so let's
first address directly knowing Earth is
Earth what is that well that is pretty
much the Right View that is the soap's
recognition through yonara that say
perceiving Earth he
knows that that Earth that he's
attending that broad phenomenon of
solidity of of one of the the the four
Great elements that he's attending to he knows
elements that he's attending to he knows
that its origin is its
manifestation is its
impermanence he knows that because
things are manifested their
manifestation is there um anicha he
doesn't need to wait for those things to
last to persist to deern them to see how
they end he knows that simply whatever
doesn't matter how long it lasts doesn't
matter what direction it goes what
matters is that it is and because it is
that's why it it's impermanent not
because because it will later on cease
that's why the when the the inside of
soan is described like or whatever well
usually translated uh whatever has the
nature of arising has the nature of
ceasing more accurately more acutely
it's like whatever has the nature to
manifest its
manifestation is its ending
manifestation carries its end because it
came on its
own so that's what it means to directly
know Earth is Earth or water is water or
brahmas is brahmas or nibana is nibana
for that matter the recognition that
manifestation that you're perceiving is
already implying its impermanence having
directly known Earth is Earth the Buddha
says let him not conceive Earth so how
does he then not conceive he should not
conceive it well he should not conceive
it by not uh lapsing from by not
ignoring that that Earth is impermanent
due to its own manifest ation doesn't
matter how long it lasts and how
permanent it might seem permanence is
seen as man something that's manifested
and on the level of that
manifestation things are impermanent
because they're
manifested and so that's the second part
is when he then encourages him to not
like psychologize having having
understood let me not do this and then
let me not do that but more like to
encourages him to make the effort to
sustain the direct knowledge of
phenomena as
phenomena as the other sutas described
through keeping the precepts neapa the
thoughts of renunciation seclusion and
withdrawal so those secondary efforts so
to speak would protect that context and
bring that knowledge of Earth is earth
water as water fire as fire to
frish and then he will not even have to
think all this Earth or this phenomenon
I'm perceiving are not mine they won't
be his because by directly seeing his
UNC conceiving them by UNC conceiving
them there is no implicit ownership
without implicit ownership there is no
Delight as I said for the PJ you already
start with the Delight
so for aana although in that broad
fundamental sense he has understood the
nature of perception on a more immediate
level he still might he still will have
for as long as he's not an Arun uh
Delight in this or that some habits of
delight in other inferior things things
that are secondary so he needs to
protect the context so that even those
habits of delight and finding pleasure
in things that are fundamentally
directly known as
unable um he needs to protect this
context for a while until it sort of
seeps into everything that's why the the
encouragement towards the practice of
the noble a for path and so on it's more
like just the the encouragement of a
certain lifestyle that can then bring
his understanding his direct knowledge
of Earth is Earth to
fulfillment and uh proof of that is when
the Buddha describes later on arant in
the Buddha they also directly know Earth
is Earth so that's the common thread the
inside into Earth as
Earth it's impermanent because it's
manifested no other reason required is
the Insight that's in common to a uh
from a soana all the way to the Buddha
so it's the same way of perceiving
things the difference at the end of the
spectrum where Arun is is that that
insight has been developed has been
brought to fulfillment so sodan is
encouraged to protect it nourish it feed
it so that that Insight then takes over
in regard to everything and all the
habits of delight and ownership are
uprooted so it's not a a psychologizing
method that he needs to keep telling
himself um in order to develop it and
then it says like why is that why the
budha encourages him then to protect the
context and and practice it and and and
and grow it so that he may completely
understand what he understood over there
so he understood it but not to its
fulfillment and then he goes obviously
list all these factors sorry all these
other phenomena nibana is
phenomena nibana is
nibana and so on Arun among who
perfected with defilements ended who has
completed the spiritual journey done
what has to be done laid down the burden
achieved the true goal arly exhausted
the F of being is rightly free through
the ultimate knowledge he also Direct ly
knows Earth is Earth so there is nothing
that he knows behind that Earth it's not
like he discovered a transcendental
reality he knows Earth is Earth by
seeing the Consciousness outside of the
Aggregates the pure awareness and so on
that's completely the contradiction in
terms he knows Earth is Earth he knows
brahmas as brahmas he knows neither
perception whatever experience might
arise he knows it in he knows it in its
manifestation nothing else required
having directly known it he doesn't
conceive it so the Buddha doesn't need
to encourage him oh he should not
conceive it he should make the effort to
prevent conceiving to kind
of take place again and grow further and
so on so having directly known Earth is
Earth he does not conceive it does not
conceive in it from it he does not
conceive it as his and he does not
Delight why because he has completely
understood it so then he lists continues listing um
it so then he lists continues listing um
few more instances of an Arun um and
then instead of like saying because he
fully understood it it's because he he's
fully free from greed then because he's
fully free from hatred he's fully free
from delusion other words he's fully
understood it um so let me just go to the next
page yeah so free from hate and free
from delusion uh and then he goes about talks
delusion uh and then he goes about talks
about the Buddha they realized the
affected one fully awakened he also
directly knows Earth is Earth having
directly known it he does not conceive
it does not conceive in it apart from it
does not con it as mine there's not
Delight in it why because the the Buddha
has completely understood it to the end
and then
adds the suta has these further
knowledges um that the Buddha so he
understood it completely to the end then
the Buddha also understood that the
light is the root of
suffering so the presence of delight as
I said implies the presence of ownership
which implies a conceiving one of these
um and that is the root of
suffering if that Delight is prevented
from spreading and growing one's
suffering will diminish even for a
pugena now if one suffering diminish in that
now if one suffering diminish in that
sense through not being proliferated
through Perpetual Delight that's not
kept in check then mind is developed
which means then even pugena would be
closer to understand that Delight is
root of
suffering that there is
no Delight that does not imply craving
impossible and basically the closer to
that simultaneous recognition of
presence of delight means presence of
suffering pujja is getting closer to
understanding of the Four Noble
Truths so then says the Buddha has
understood the light is the root of
suffering and thus that with being there
is birth and whatever is born gets old
and dies in other words he's describing
here the entire scope of a human life
again that is present through your
Delight here and now you're
delighting implies the ownership which
implies your sense of self which implies
your own sense of being here and now and
that which is born into this plane like
from birth till basically till till the
end when you die means that anything
that that happens anything that exists
with in that um anything that that whole
plane is liable to you will partake in
that liability so by freeing yourself from
liability so by freeing yourself from
theight here and now you can't undo your
birth and you can't prevent the body
from breaking apart and Aggregates sort
of passing away but if you remove the
light you remove the ownership if there
is no ownership means this whole domain
destined to the destruction and
decomposition does not belong to you
which means whatever it's waiting
to happen to it won't be your problem
won't be happening to it to you that's
why in the suas when the Buddha talks
about death of an Arun when anaran dies
he doesn't use the word death he he
refers to it as the breakup of the
Aggregates but puj dies so death implies
the ownership of that which is liable to
die at any given moment freedom from
ownership means oh it's just these
Aggregates they came together they break
apart but there is no owner there there
is no being is extinguished so there is
no death applicable
um so yeah so it basically describes the
Buddha describes his understanding and
then it says that the monks did not
Delight in what the Buddha
said and uh this could possibly mean
that uh it simply went over their heads
in its own kind of not not completely
over the heads but to a degree like as I
said you know like we have now these
sutas it's all written down you can
study you can scroll you can reread but
back then imagine you listening the
Buddha and obviously these whole records
of this are like kind of templates of
memories of
instruction obviously the details of
speech that are not contained so imagine
you were there listening to something as
in comprehensive as
this pointing to like for example
pointing to not just the delight and
ownership but the implicit conceiving of
it
um in all the directions in all the
permutations in all the ways all the
things that could be perceived it's a
bit much to take there and then so the
monks that were listening to this were
probably already a noble disciples at
least he wouldn't have been teaching
these two puas because he would make no
difference to them but they didn't
Delight because he just there was so
much to
unpack and uh the point like as I said
before see talks about conceiving he
talks about a structural existence of
your ownership that implies conceiving
that on top of it has the implicit
Delight but even for a noble disciple if
was somebody with the Right View that if
he were to approach it he won't see
these conceiving like he can later
distinguish them on account of the
instruction like from the suta for
example but all he sees is his Delight
in things and then he can discern the
the simultaneously present sense of
ownership sense of I am so when then the
Buddha talks about what within that well
that's like way past their like
practical recognition so they didn't
Delight in the words but um that's not
to say that they obviously did not
understand the framework of what he was
saying here they just couldn't get all
the
details so so that would conclude the uh
the Mula paraya suta and
um obviously
again if say somebody who doesn't have
the right view come across the suta it
you know it
doesn't it doesn't really it doesn't
really have uh carries that uh like a
value of the practical
application uh but that doesn't mean
that you shouldn't be trying to
understand it because even a putuj could
benefit from understanding that for
example nibana is not the a mystical
experience outside of these Aggregates
that you somehow Escape into I mean
that's what it would have said like for
as far as the language and the
designation goes for as far as basically
you can perceive phenomena and call them
a name even if it's the the most General
broadest ambiguous name it is really
such and as far as the designation and
the language go that's how far tagata
has understood so that's how far he has laid
understood so that's how far he has laid
out the teaching in other words there is
no secret reality behind the conventions
and Concepts as sometimes it is thought
and uh and there and and there is no
problem with that you don't need a
secret reality because again even if
it's a if it's a hidden reality that you
discover it's still going to be
something you perceive which means it's
not hidden it was only relatively hidden
it's still within the five agregates
within the perception within so there's
no outside of you and uh so simply by
studying the suta by recognizing what
even if it's the the novelty of the
perceiving of the Gods and uh and
streaming Radiance novelty is just generated by
Radiance novelty is just generated by
what you were like um by your common
perception but fundamental whether it's
a common or uncommon perception whether
it's mundane or super mundane whether
it's the novelty of the experience
perceptions there and you realize it's
not about the specific experience
experiences of you know some people
think the attainments will be the
specific energies and and and new
experiences coming over and so on it
doesn't matter how new it is that's
never where the emphasis was or should
be the emphasis is whether it's new or
old personal impersonal
lofty uh the most Sublime experience I
ever had experience is there as such
it's manifested as such it's impermanent
so you stop being concerned about the
content of your experience which means
you'll stop looking for neana outside of
this content outside of the
mundane and when you stop looking
outside of it outside of the mundane you
get to understand the mundane and you
get to understand the nature of
perception on account of mundane and
that's it's necessary then you will
directly know Earth is Earth you will
directly know seen is seen heard is
heard doesn't matter you don't need a
special perception to tell you the truth
because that's never where the emphasis
was that's never where the problem was
that's why that's not the root of all
the Buddha didn't say see the root of
all these things it's this another thing
that you perceive specially Underneath
It All no he said even perceiving the
all even perceiving the Oneness the
diversity the unity the nibana
it's the perception of it affected with
ignorance for putuj or direct knowledge
for a noble disciple and an arant